Guide to the Rice Institute/Rice University Charter Trial records, 1963 - 1998 UA 275
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice Institute/Rice University Charter Trial records
1963-1998
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
UA 275
2.5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
These records reflect the court proceedings of and alumni and public response to Rice Institute's Charter trial of 1964 and later appeals and judgments. The lawsuit was brought by the Rice Institute Trustees seeking to alter the Institute's original charter to allow admission of students of color and to enable the school to charge tuition. Additional changes to the charter in 1982 and 1998 relating to structure of the board of trustees and the university's legal ability to borrow money are also documented here.
Biographical / Historical
The original charter for the Rice Institute was drawn from an indenture written by William Marsh Rice in 1891 and stated that the institute would be open to "white inhabitants of Houston and Texas" for "free tuition". The trustees of the Rice Institute petitioned the courts in February 1963 as a request for declaratory order confirming that the board of trustees in fact already possessed the authority and prerogative under the Charter to amend the same (which multiple courts subsequently affirmed). The Rice Board of Trustees was unanimous in supporting this suit, claiming that such actions were necessary in order to carry out William Marsh Rice's primary intent to establish an educational institution of the first class. Rice President Kenneth Pitzer was also in full support of this initiative. Rice was unable to compete for grant funding because it did not charge tuition to students, and was under increasing pressure by the civil rights movement to admit students based on merit and without regard to race. Rice was among the last of the southern colleges and universities to admit students of color.
In summer 1963, two Rice alumni, John B. Coffee and Val T. Billups filed a petition intervening in the suit and challenging the trustees' position. In January 1964, a group of Rice University alumni filed a petition supporting the trustees' position and opposing Coffee and Billups. Later that month, Coffee and Billups filed an amended petition further outlining their points.
The case went to District Judge William M. Holland's court on Feb. 10, 1964 and a verdict favorable to Rice was handed down on March 9, 1964.
Later in 1964, the first civil court of appeals affirmed District Judge William M. Holland's ruling. In 1965, the first civil court of appeals dismissed an appeal by two Rice alumni, John B. Coffee and Val T. Billups (begun in summer 1963), ruling that the two men had no justifiable interest in the case. Coffee and Billups then appealed to the Texas Supreme Court, who sent the case back to the appeals court, claiming it should heard the case in the first place.
Tuition was charged to students who could afford it beginning in 1965. In fall 1965, Rice's first two African American undergraduate freshmen were admitted and began classes. One of them was a woman, Jacqueline McCauley of Houston. However, Rice's first African American student was actually admitted in 1963, when Raymond Lewis Johnson was admitted to the Math Department in pursuit of a master's degree. As part of these changes to the charter, Rice Institute became known as Rice University.
Prior to this charter lawsuit, Rice did on occasion ignore the Caucasian rule and admit male students of color, including Charles S. Chan of Houston who graduated in 1941 with a B.S. in architectural engineering.
In October 1966, the appeals court upheld Judge Holland's 1964 ruling in favor of Rice Institute. In February 1967, the Texas Supreme Court denied a writ of error in the lawsuit filed by alumni Coffee and Billups.
A 1982 lawsuit over the charter provision requiring all seven trustees to live in Houston was overturned. Further amendments to the charter were made in 1998, enabling the expansion of the Board of Trustees from seven to a maximum of twenty-five and allowing Rice to incur debt by borrowing money or using tax-free bonds to finance large projects such as construction.
Scope and Contents
These records reflect the court proceedings of and alumni and public response to Rice Institute's Charter trial of 1964 and later appeals and judgments. The 1964 lawsuit was brought by the Rice Institute trustees seeking to alter the Institute's original charter to allow admission of students of color and to enable the school to charge tuition. Additional changes to the charter in 1982 and 1998 are also documented here. Formats include legal documents, notes, correspondence, newsclippings, and press releases.
Access Restrictions
The materials are open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the President's office, 2002.
Related Material
See "At a most uncomfortable speed: the desegregation of the South's private universities, 1945-1964", by Melissa Fitzsimmons Kean, Ph.D. dissertation, Rice University, History Dept., 2000. (Fondren call # THESIS HIST. 2000 Kean)
Related Materials
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/109678
Index Terms
Subjects
Education; Rice University -- History; Segregation in higher education; Civil rights -- Texas; Universities and colleges; Right to education; Courts; Civil rights
Document Types
legal documents; reports; letters (correspondence); notes
- Series I: Lawsuit and background materials, 1963-1964; 158127
  - Suit as filed and amended, 1963-1964; 158129 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rice President Pitzer's statement on purpose of Rice charter suit, 158153 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Administrative resolution, 158154 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - William Marsh Rice will extracts, 158155 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Charter, original copies and updated versions, 158156 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - By-laws, 158157 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Background material: Rice board minutes, 158158 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Background material: Rice income / expenditures, grants, 158159 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Background material: Rice departmental / committee policies, directory, 158160 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II: Trial documents, 1963-1964; 158165
  - Trial exhibits, 1963-1964; 158167 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Trial exhibit: charter original copy, 158168 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Trial testimony, 158173 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Shorthand notebook of trial proceedings, 158174 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Shorthand notebook of trial proceedings, 158175 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series III: Correspondence, 158187
  - Correspondence, 1964-1988; 158188 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Press releases and newsclippings, 1963-1998; 158189
  - Press releases, 1982-1998; 158191 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Newsclippings, 1963-1966; 158193 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series V: Court Judgment, 1964; 158220
  - Court judgment, 1964; 158222 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series VI: Alumni response and appeal, 1963-1964; 158225
  - Alumni response. Organized efforts by alumni to support the charter changes., 1963; 158227 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Appeal (Coffee vs. Rice), 158228 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Related records, 158229 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series VII: Articles of Incorporation, 1998; 158231
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1998; 158233 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series VIII: President Kenneth Pitzer correspondence, memoranda, and trial materials, 1962-1968; 158430
  General
  Access to these records requires written permission from the President's Office. Contact Woodson staff for instructions.
  - Baker, Botts, Shepherd & Coates Communications, 1962-1968; 158431 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Coffee & Aronson, 1963-1967; 158432 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Alumni & Public Reaction, 1963; 158433 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Alumni & Public Reaction, 1964-1967; 158435 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Faculty, 1964; 158436 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Governors, 1963 - 1965; 158437 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Information Requests & Replies, 1963-1967; 158438 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Intervenors, 1963-1964; 158439 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Pitzer notes, 1963-1964; 158440 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Publicity, 1964-1967; 158441 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Research: Finances & Campaign, 1965; 158442 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Research: Government & Foundations, 1963-1964; 158443 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Research: Legal Dorctrine & Precedent, 1962-1966; 158444 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Research: Rice History & Trial Documents, 1962 - 1967; 158445 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Witnesses, 1963 - 1964; 158446 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Case No. A-10719, Respondent's Reply to Application for Writ of Error, 158517 (Box 4, Item 1)
  - Case No. A-10719, Brief for Respondents, 158518 (Box 4, Item 2)
  - Case No. A-10719, Motion for Rehearing, 158519 (Box 4, Item 3)
  - Case No. 14,472, Supplemental Brief of Appellees, 158520 (Box 4, Item 4)
  - Case No. 14,472, Brief of the Appellees, 158521 (Box 4, Item 5)
  - Case No. 14,472, Brief of the Appellants, 158522 (Box 4, Item 6)
  - Case No. A-10719, Respondent's Reply to Application for Writ of Error, 158523 (Box 4, Item 7)
  - Case No. 612,668, Statement of Facts, Volume 1, 158524 (Box 4, Item 8)
  - Case No. 612,668, Statement of Facts, Volume 2, 158525 (Box 4, Item 9)
  - Case No. 612,668, Statement of Facts, Volume 3, 158526 (Box 4, Item 10)
  - Case No. 612,668, Statement of Facts, Volume 4, 158527 (Box 4, Item 11)
  - Case No. 612,668, Jury Arguments, 158528 (Box 4, Item 12)
  - Case No. 612,668, Harry Hunt Ransom Testimony, 158529 (Box 4, Item 13)
  - Resolution of the Board of Governors, 1966; 158530 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Court Filings/ Case No. 612,668, 1963; 158531 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Testimony/ Kenneth Pitzer, 1964; 158532 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Copies of Trial Documents/ Kenneth Pitzer, 158533 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Court Filings/ Case No. 14,472, 1963 - 1966; 158534 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Court Filings/ Case No. A-10719, 1966; 158535 (Box 5, Folder 6)